Finding Aid for Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center records, 1988-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center records, 1988-1999
Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center.
2 linear feet
0112 Bimu 2
MADRC began in 1989 at the University of Michigan with funding from the National Institute on Aging. Goals of the center include promoting research and education on Alzheimer's disease and related dementias with an emphasis on clinical and basic research. Records pertain to the administration of the center, and include research grants, satellite clinic training material, and material from conferences, committees and seminars devoted to promoting recent findings in Alzheimer's research and treatment.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor 8981 ) was received from the Michigan Alzheimer’s Disease Research Center in June 2000
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- removed to vault.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (MADRC) was started in 1989 at the University of Michigan with funding from the National Institute on Aging. The overall goal of the center is to "promote research and education on Alzheimer's disease and related dementias and to assure the dissemination amongst scientists, physicians and caregivers in Michigan of state-of-the-art methods of evaluation and care by its educational activities." (Box 1, Original grant, Introduction). Emphasis is placed on both clinical and fundamental scientific research.
MADRC was first led by director Dr. Anne B. Young and co-director Dr. Sid Gilman, both of the Department of Neurology at the University of Michigan. In the beginning, it was a "small center based primarily within the Department of Neurology," but over time it developed more ties with other university programs, in addition to being awarded two satellite diagnostic and treatment centers, one in Detroit in 1991 and the other in Traverse City in 1992 (Box 1, Competing renewal, Introductory material). The mission of the Metro-Detroit Satellite Diagnostic and Treatment Center (SDTC) is to reach out to the traditionally underserved African American elderly population of Detroit, while the Northern Michigan SDTC targets the also-neglected rural elderly.
In 1991, Anne Young left U-M for a position in Massachusetts, and Sid Gilman took over as director. Dr. Norman Foster serves as co-director of MADRC and director of the Clinical Core. Directors of the Metro-Detroit SDTC have been Harvey Altman, Ph.D., from 1991 to September 1993 and Peter LeWitt, M.D., from October 1993 on.
Originally, MADRC consisted of four cores: the Clinical Core, the Neuropathology Core, the Administrative Core, and the Research Training and Information Transfer Core (later called the Education Core or the Education Training and Information Transfer Core). The number of cores has fluctuated somewhat, with the addition of the Biostatistics Core and the Neuropsychology Core in 1994. Sometime after that, the number of cores went down to five, with the dropping of the Neuropsychology Core. MADRC's basic structure of division into cores, however, remains constant.
The MADRC records come from the Administrative Core of the MADRC, which oversees all of the other cores. Because of the Administrative Core's coordinating role, the record group contains information pertaining to the activities of all the cores. The arrangement of the record group reflects the original order of the material, which was contained in three-ring binders with tabbed divisions. The records of the MADRC date from 1988 to 1999 and measure two linear feet. The record group is divided into three series: Grants, Satellite Clinics, and Conferences, Committees, and Networks. Much of the material consists of "stand-alone" files, such as grant applications and seminar documentation, which are arranged topically and have tables of contents to guide the reader. The rest of the material, correspondence and the like, is arranged chronologically, with the inclusion of some undated material.
Subjects:
Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center.; Alzheimer's disease.; Alzheimer's disease--Michigan.; Senile dementia.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Grants
  The Grants series (.8 linear feet) consists of five grant applications: the original grant submitted to the National Institute on Aging in 1989, three non-competing grant renewal applications submitted from 1990 through 1993, and a competing renewal application for 1994 to 1999. The "Introduction" sections of each grant application contain useful summaries of MADRC's main activities and its background. The 1991 non-competing renewal includes copies of overhead transparencies of the "ADRC Investigator's Meeting."
  - Original Grant 1988-1990 (portfolio 1 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Introduction (Box 1)
      (includes program description, budgets, biographical sketches of staff)
    - Core A: Clinical Core (Box 1)
    - Core B: Neuropathology Core (Box 1)
    - Core C: Administrative Core (Box 1)
    - Core D: Research Training and Information Transfer Core (Box 1)
    - Project 1: "Motor Correlates of Dementia," Sid Gilman, M.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 2: "Neuropharmacologic Challenges in Dementia," Norman L. Foster, M.D. (Box 1)
  - Original grant 1988-1990 (portfolio 2 of 2)
    - Project 3: "Dopaminergic and Cholinergic Markers in Dementia," John B. Penney, M.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 4: "Glutamate Receptors in the Dementias," Anne B. Young, M.D., Ph.D. (Box 1)
    - Pilot projects: Feasibility proposals (Box 1)
    - Pink sheets: initial critiques of proposal and related correspondence (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous: miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1)
    - Appendices (Box 1)
  - Non-competing renewal 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Non-competing renewal 1991-1992
    - 1991 renewal (Box 1)
    - Pilot projects (Box 1)
    - Overheads: copies of overhead transparencies for the ADRC Investigator's Meeting undated (Box 1)
  - Non-competing renewal 1993 (Box 1)
  - Competing renewal 1994-1999
    - Budget: budget drafts and related correspondence (Box 1)
      (items in pocket of original binder but not included in the grant renewal application)
    - Biographical sketches (Box 1)
    - Other support (Box 1)
      (details researchers' other projects and funding sources)
    - Introductory material: general explanation of MADRC (Box 1)
    - Core A: Administrative Core (Box 1)
    - Core B: Clinical Core (Box 1)
    - Core C: Neuropathology Core (Box 1)
    - Core D: Education and Information Transfer Core (Box 1)
    - Core E: Neuropsychology Core (Box 1)
    - Core F: Biostatistics Core (Box 1)
    - Project 1: "Benzodiazepine Receptors in Neurodegenerative Diseases," Sid Gilman, M.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 2: "Neuropharmacologic Challenges in Dementia," Norman L. Foster, M.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 3: "Presynaptic Neurochemical Markers," Kirk Frey, M.D., Ph.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 4: "The Pathology of Diffuse Lewy Body Disease," Anders A.F. Sima, M.D., Ph.D. (Box 1)
  - Competing renewal 1994-1999 (cont.)
    - Project 5: "Chronic Striatal Quinolinate," Roger L. Albin, M.D. (Box 1)
    - Project 6: "Statewide Public Opinion Survey of Alzheimer's Disease," Cathleen M. Connell, Ph.D. (Box 1)
    - Supplement 1 (Box 1)
    - Supplement 2 (Box 1)
    - Review: review procedures for grant applications (Box 1)
- Satellite Clinics
  The Satellite Clinics series (.6 linear feet) contains documentation on MADRC's two satellite clinics, the Metro-Detroit SDTC and the Northern Michigan SDTC in Traverse City. In some cases the satellite clinics are also referred to as ADRCs, or Alzheimer's Disease Research Centers. Files include the manuals for a satellite center training seminar held February 9-11, 1993, and a satellite center orientation meeting held August 4, 1995; the Satellite documentation file, which consists mainly of correspondence relating to both SDTCs; and correspondence and miscellaneous files for both the Metro-Detroit and the Traverse City satellite clinics.
  The Metro-Detroit SDTC experienced some problems with staffing, as well as with recruiting minority patients, the latter problem due partly to distrust of the medical establishment within the minority community. These issues are discussed in the Metro-Detroit SDTC files in this series.
  - Satellite training manual February 9-11, 1993
    - Staff, cores, and map (Box 1)
    - Documentation and forms (Box 1)
    - Enrollment packet (Box 1)
    - Research projects (Box 1)
    - Case studies (Box 1)
    - Reference lists (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous: includes forms and University of Michigan publications
      - "Guidelines for the Responsible Conduct of Research" (Box 1)
      - "Information About Brain Autopsy (Box 1)
      - Patient procedures and forms (Box 1)
  - Satellite orientation August 4, 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1. Orientation Agenda & Staff Directory (Box 2)
    - 2. MADRC/Core Descriptions (Box 2)
    - 3. Communication Links (Box 2)
    - 4. MADRC Database and Clinical Core Documentation (Box 2)
    - 5. Enrollment Packet (Box 2)
    - 6. Associated Clinical Research Studies (Box 2)
    - 7. Community Advisory Committee (Box 2)
    - 8. Articles on Minority Issues in AD (Box 2)
    - 9. Articles on Autopsy and AD (Box 2)
    - 10. Reference Lists (Box 2)
  - Satellite documentation 1991-1993
    (mainly correspondence)
    - Traverse City (Box 2)
    - Detroit Satellite Diagnostic and Treatment Center (Box 2)
    - Detroit Institutional Review Board (IRB) (Box 2)
  - Metro-Detroit Satellite Diagnostic and Treatment Center
    - Correspondence 1993-1995 (Box 2)
    - Director personnel file July-September 1993
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2023 ]
      (Restricted; removed to vault storage.)
    - Miscellany (Box 2)
  - Norman Foster correspondence 1993-1996 correspondence pertaining to the Metro-Detroit SDTC (Box 2)
  - Northern Michigan Satellite Diagnostic and Treatment Center
    - Correspondence 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - Miscellany (Box 2)
- Conferences, Committees, and Networks
  The final series consists of items pertaining to Conferences, Committees, and Networks (.6 linear feet) that MADRC has organized or participated in. The conference included is the Geriatric Research Education and Clinical Center Conference of 1992. Committees and networks consist of the following: the Michigan Dementia Services Coordinating Committee (MDSCC), the Michigan Dementia Postmortem Network (MDPN), and the Dementia Subcommittee of the Chronic Disease Advisory Committee (CDAC). The activities of all of these bodies are connected and in many cases overlap.
  The Michigan Dementia Services Coordinating Committee files contain correspondence, minutes, and reports from 1994-1999. MDSCC is a unit of the Michigan Dementia Program, which in turn is under the authority of the Michigan Public Health Institute. MDSCC's role is promoting information and referral services among Michigan groups researching and treating dementia. MADRC leaders Sid Gilman and Norman Foster are active in this committee as well. The annual files contain correspondence as well as minutes and reports from MDSCC meetings. In addition, there are items pertaining to the activities of other committees with which MDSCC is involved.
  The Chronic Disease Advisory Committee was established in 1978 by the Michigan Department of Public Health under a mandate of the Public Health Code. The committee is appointed by the governor with state senate approval. In choosing committee members, attempts are made to provide balance in terms of geographical location, professional background, and the range of chronic diseases that are studied. The items in this file actually relate mainly to the work of the Dementia Subcommittee of CDAC and cover the period from 1988 to 1994. CDAC is described as having a "close, cooperative working relationship with the MADRC" (Box 2, CDAC, July 8, 1991 letter to W. Loring Cloud of the Upjohn Company). Sid Gilman of MADRC serves as head of the Dementia Subcommittee of CDAC, and Norman Foster is a CDAC member. Other MADRC staff members are involved as well.
  The Dementia Subcommittee of CDAC began in 1987 on the recommendation of a state task force on Alzheimer's disease and related illnesses. The Dementia Subcommittee is the official advisory body to the Michigan Dementia Program (MDP). Included in the files are reference materials from a workgroup held November 21, 1991, which give documentation on the startup and management of MDP's Diagnostic and Assessment Network for Dementia. There is also a Dementia Subcommittee general administrative file containing correspondence, minutes, and newsletters.
  The Dementia Subcommittee is also in charge of the Michigan Dementia Postmortem Network, which has its own separate file. The MDPN serves as a way to coordinate brain autopsy work on Alzheimer's disease victims on a statewide level and to increase the number of enrollees in the program. Included are a reference file, which has material from a November 14, 1990 workgroup and related follow-up items, and an administrative file which covers the period from 1992 to 1999.
  - Ann Arbor Geriatric Research Education and Clinical Center (GRECC) and Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (MADRC) Conference: Fourth Annual Seminar in Geriatrics Program Development, "Dementia: Focus on Assessment and Management of Older Adults," April 14, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Dementia Services Coordinating Committee (DSCC): correspondence, minutes, activity reports, 3 folders
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - Chronic Disease Advisory Committee (CDAC) 1988-1994 (Box 2)
    (primarily correspondence)
  - Chronic Disease Advisory Committee, Dementia Subcommittee
    - Michigan Diagnostic and Assessment Network reference materials November 20, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Administrative file: correspondence, minutes, newsletters, plan drafts 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Dementia Postmortem Network (MDPN)
    - Reference materials 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Administrative file: correspondence, minutes, newsletter, program outlines, activity reports 1992-1999 (Box 2)
      (no items from 1998 one item from 1999)
- Printed
  - Newsletters
    - Bridges, circa 1997 (Box 2)